John Neagle Papers 1817-1865 Mss.B.N125.p
American Philosophical Society
John Neagle Papers
1817-1865
Mss.B.N125.p
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
John Neagle was among the better known portrait painters in Philadelphia during the first half of the nineteenth century and was the husband of Thomas Sully's niece, Mary C. Sully. The Neagle Papers is a small assemblage of personal correspondence, documents, and notes assembled by Neagle during his career. The letters are primarily of a personal nature, but along with the five bound volumes, offer insight into Neagle's study of painting and the techniques he employed. Included among the bound volumes are recipes for varnish, megellup, and drying oils and notes on watercolor painting.
Neagle, John, 1796-1865
Bibliography
Torchia, Robert, John Neagle: Philadelphia PortraitPainter (Philadelphia: HSP, 1989). Call no.: B N25t
Early American History Note
The John Neagle Papers provides a window into the world and the work of this nineteenth century portrait painter. The collection contains many insights on how Neagle approached his craft. It begins with an interesting notebook he kept on the history of painting. This volume is dated 1817. It traces the history of art from Etruria to the present. He discusses renaissance artists in some depth, such as Michelangelo and Raphael. He also discusses modern artistic training, mentioning the types of study done in Rome and France. Other notebooks contain essays Neagle wrote on art and artists, such as “hints for a painter.” His notebook “Lessons on Landscape Painting” include a few watercolors that appear to be copies of landscape work done by Thomas Sully.
The letters in the collection often deal with Neagle and his family. It also contains a Valentine’s Day poem sent to him, a lease that Neagle took out from Matthew Carey for his house on Walnut St., and various broadsides and stock certificates.
Finally, the collection contains what appears to be an autobiographical “sketch” written by Neagle in the 1850s and one small sketch of “Jim Brown” from 1861.
Related Archival Materials note
Additional Neagle Papers are located at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania ( Collection2112), which also houses Neagle's commonplace book ( Collection448)
Existence and Location of Copies note
Series II is available on microfilm (Film 1388)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Series II was acquired in 1959; Series I was purchased at Sotheby's, 1985.
Scope and Contents note
The Neagle Papers contains less than 0.25 linear feet of personal letters and documents and five notebooks relating to the life and work of the painter, John Neagle. The letters to his wife and children are affectionate, intimate, and generally relate strictly to personal or family matters, such as planning vacations or excursions. There are membership certificates in the Masonic Grand Lodge of Pennsylvania and a share in the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts.
Several letters, however, provide glimpses into Neagle's work, including a letter from Kentucky, March 18, 1843, notifying Levi Dickson that he had completed his portrait of Henry Clay (now in the Union League), and letter written to Sully in 1838, congratulating him on winning a commission to paint Queen Victoria. In this letter, Neagle writes:
The bound volumes offer valuable insights into Neagle's artistic techniques. The volumes include recipes for megellup, varnishes, and drying oils, instructions for cleaning and restoring works of art, notes on watercolor and landscape techniques employed by John Varley, Thomas Sully, and others, and Neagle's "Hints for a painter with regard to his method of study."
Biographical/Historical note
Like Benjamin Franklin before him, John Neagle was a Bostonian by birth and a Philadelphian by nature. One of Philadelphia's better known portrait painters during the first half of the nineteenth century and a promoter of the fine arts, Neagle was born into a family of middling means in 1796. After his father, Maurice, an Irish immigrant, died in 1800, John was raised in Philadelphia. In his autobiography, Neagle describes becoming obsessed with drawing at an early age, despite little family encouragement.
While serving as an apprentice to the "coach and ornamental painter," Thomas Wilson, Neagle began to explore the possibility of painting as a career. Through Wilson, Neagle was introduced to the portrait painter Bass Otis, whose work, he wrote, "set me on fire." After two months study with Otis, and committed research on his own, Neagle committed himself to becoming a portrait painter.
Having earned praise for his ambition and the quality of his work, Neagle turned away from coach painting and at the end of his apprenticeship in 1818, he struck out for Lexington, Kentucky, in the hopes of establishing himself in business. Finding that another painter, Matthew Harris Jouett, was already well entrenched there, Neagle moved to New Orleans, where he was again thwarted by the competition, before returning to Philadelphia.
In his home city, Neagle's career slowly began to develop. Exhibiting at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts from 1821 on, and becoming the protege of Thomas Sully by 1824, Neagle continued his studies. In 1825, he traveled to Boston to study with Gilbert Stuart for a year, returning to Philadelphia to marry Mary Chester Sully, Sully's niece and stepdaughter.
Over the next decade, Neagle worked in both New York and Philadelphia, producing his best known works, including Pat Lyon at the Forge and his portrait ofthe physician, William Potts Dewees (1833). In 1842, he was commissioned topaint his last great work, the massive portrait of Henry Clay that now hangs inthe Union League of Philadelphia.
Neagle's artistic output began to wane following the death of his wife in 1845, and he began gradually to withdraw from public life. In the late 1850s, he suffered a severe stroke which left him partially paralyzed. He died at home in Philadelphia on September 17, 1865.
Neagle family; Neagle, Mary Chester Sully; Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts.; Sully family; Sully, Thomas, 1783-1872; Varley, John, 1778-1842; Art; Artists' materials; Artists--Pennsylvania; Autobiographies.; Autobiography; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Landscape painting; Literature, Arts, and Culture; Manuscript Essays; Notebooks; Painting--Study and teaching; Recipes; Sketchbooks; Valentines; Watercolor paintings; Whist
- Series I. Correspondence and notes, 1817-1865; 37 items; 0.25 linear feet
  - History of Painting (notebook), 1817 May 30; 51p.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Fragmentary notes written at age 19, based on reading on the lives of Raphael, Michaelangelo, the Carraccis, Titian, Rubens, LeBrun, and Reynolds.
  - Membership certificate in Freemasons, 1818 May 6; Grand Lodge of Pennsylvania (Box 1)
  - ADS lease to John Neagle and George Catlin, 1822 October 21; Carey, Matthew (Box 1)
    Lease of house at 116 Walnut Street to Neagle and Catlin for one year. "The said Neagle & Catlin hereby pledge themselves to keep the house in good order."
  - ALS to Mary C. Sully, 1825 August 3; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Moggy,(i.e Mary C. Sully), 1825 December 10; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Journal (fragments), 1826 May 26-1832 August 14; 7p.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
    The remainder of the journal is located in the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, filed with the "Blotter Book."
  - ALS to John Neagle, 1826 August 1826; Ennis, Susan (Box 1)
  - ALS to John Neagle, 1826?; Neagle, Alfred (Box 1)
  - ALS to Thomas Sully, 1838 February 6; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
    Written on back of a printed prospectus, "John Neagle Proposes to Publish, By Subscription, A Series of Well Engraved Portraits of the Medical Professors of the University of Pennsylvania, From original Paintings, To Be Executed By Himself, Expressly for the Work."
  - ALS to Blanch Sully, 1838 June 23; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Levi Dickson, 1843 March 18; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to "children", 1844 August; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to John Neagle, 1846 April 21; Tiers, Arundius (Box 1)
  - AL to John Neagle, 1850 February 14; E.C. (Box 1)
  - Stock Certificate, 1850 May 29; Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. (Box 1)
  - ALS to "children", 1850 August 9; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to "children", 1850 August 13; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Sally Sully, 1850 August 19; Sully, Mary C. (Box 1)
  - ALS to Bettie and Sallie Neagle, 1850 August 19; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript sketches of my career as an artist, 1850?; 7p.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Account of an Annuity settled by the late Levi Taylor, 1852 July 14 (Box 1)
  - Memorandum of the illness and death of Margaret Dickson Neagle (called "Moggie"), daughter of John Neagle, Artist, & Mary Chester Sully, 1853 June 26; 3p. (Box 1)
  - ALS to "children", 1855 August 3; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to "children", 1855 August 4; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Susan Neagle?, 1859 April 25; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Envelope--G. Robertson to John Neagle, 1859 September 8 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Mary Neagle, 1861 April 2; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Sketch of Jim Brown, 1861; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
    Pencil sketch on back of small envelope
  - DS Invoice for funeral of John Neagle, 1865 September 17; Moore, David P. (Box 1)
  - Envelope--John Neagle to Elizabeth I. Neagle and sisters (Box 1)
  - ALS to John Neagle, n.d.; Carey, Henry C. (Box 1)
  - Clipped signatures, n.d.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Neagle family genealogical material, n.d. (Box 1)
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, n.d.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Sully's advice about cleaning, varnishing, and restoring paintings, 5p.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Box 1)
    Includes notes on Sully's techniques, palette.
  - Sully family genealogical material, n.d.; 6p. (Box 1)
  - Sully family list of births, deaths and marriages (Box 1)
- Series II. Bound volumes, 1825-1850; 5 vols.
  - On Whist, 1850; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Volume 1)
  - Receipts for making Megellup, Varnish, & Drying Oil; also for cleaning pictures..., 1825; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Volume 2)
  - Hints for a painter with regard to his Method of Study, etc., n.d.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Volume 3)
  - [On artists and works of art], 1826; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Volume 4)
  - Lessons on Landscape painting... Illustrated with copies from Sully's copies, Varley and others, 1827; 27p.; Neagle, John, 1796-1865 (Volume 5)
    Includes samples of watercolor paints, copies of landscapes by John Varley, and extensive notes on the watercolor techniques employed by Varley, Sully, Titian, Rubens, and others.
    "Presented by J. Neagle to his daughter Elizabeth J. Neagle, Augt. 1842"